Are you active [music] duty, a veteran,
or PCSing to the central Texas area?
[music]
Maybe that's Fortthood, Temple, Belton,
and any of the surrounding areas, and
you're wondering how your VA home loan
benefits [music]
actually work. Can you use them more
than once? Uh, what about [music]
closing costs or down payments?
>> Yeah, VA loans are one of the most
powerful benefits to service [music]
members and veterans. There's a lot of
misinformation out there. So, today
we'll break down some of the benefits,
who can use the VA loans, and set some
of the expectations when you're looking
[music] to buy here in Central Texas.
So, hi, I'm Andrea Judy, local real
estate [music]
expert and broker here in Central Texas.
I'm here with Jacob Stutard, your VA
home lending expert. [music] Also
handles all other types of home loans,
but that's really his specialty. And
today we will be uh really breaking down
the VA home loan [music] benefits so
that you can leave here feeling really
confident about the entirety of the
process.
>> Let's do it.
>> Let's do it. [music]
>> Okay, Jacob. So, who qualifies for a VA
loan?
>> Yeah. So, active duty service members,
reser national guardsmen, [music]
certain circumstances, spouses can
qualify. If you're PCSing, if you're
post service relocating, [music]
there's many circumstances on on how
people can qualify, but the golden
ticket is to make sure you have your
certificate [music] of eligibility.
>> And I've seen you help people with that.
How do they go about knowing what
[music] that looks like or how to get
that?
>> Yeah. So, you can get your certificate
of eligibility. You can request it
through the VA loan guarantee system or
you can reach out to myself and I can
walk you through the necessary steps on
how to get that done. Okay,
>> super simple. [music]
>> Okay, so if someone received PCS orders
to come here, how soon can they start
the process with you?
>> So, as soon as you have your orders, you
can start the process. Um, the only
thing that the VA requires is that you
move in within 60 days of closing. Now,
there are exceptions to that rule, and
we can get into the details over a phone
call, but um, as soon as you get those
orders, you're you're ready to get the
ball rolling.
>> Okay, cool. [music] So really, first
step is going to be to contact Jacob,
get all of that in order, and then at
that point as your realtor, we can have
a very detailed conversation on where
you're looking to be, what your wants,
musthaves, and you know, really what's
important for [music] your circumstances
and lifestyle. We can have that
conversation, set you up to start
looking at houses. You don't need to be
here for us to do Oz. We are so
familiar, especially [music] with Fort
Hood being where it is. Not only is
Texas so friendly and um catering to its
veterans, but we're so familiar with the
process. We do a lot of helping people
when they're not here [music] and
purchasing a home.
>> Exactly. We've done plenty of closings
where they're the veterans or the
service members are still overseas or at
a different state. You can do remote
closings. There's all types of creative
ways uh to get the job done without
being actually here in person. One of
the most flexible uh benefits of using
the view [music]
>> for sure. And I know it can seem really
stressful, but once he gets, you know,
you going on the lending side, I can do
virtual showings. A lot of times people
will come down if they can for maybe a
week just to familiarize themselves with
the area, see where they like best,
maybe look at a few houses, but you
know, I have done a lot of
>> [music]
>> um virtual showing stuff to look at. So
every anything is possible.
>> Yep. We'll walk you through everything.
So you're not going to be going through
any of the process. uh by yourself,
we'll be with you every step of the way.
>> Yep. So, what are some of the biggest
myths and [music] misconceptions you've
seen about the VA uh home loan?
>> Yeah. So, you first off, you don't need
to be a first-time home buyer. You can
use your VA loan more than once, [music]
and you can even have your VA loan,
multiple VA loans at the same time, so
long you can qualify. [music] 0% down
payment is an option. You don't have to
do it, but it is one of the main
benefits of using your VA loan. [music]
There is no mortgage insurance on VA
leaps. So, no matter what your down
payment percentage is, [music]
you're not going to have any mortgage
insurance. The VA funding fee, you can
roll that into the loan amount. Uh the
VA funding fee, you can be exempt if you
have a service connected disability
rating. So, there's some perks to that
as well.
>> Yeah, I hear all the time people say,
"Well, I've already used my VA home
loan. I can't use it again." Or I've
even had people call [music] and they
drop in there that they're actively
working at Fort Hood and are talking
about a conventional loan and they've
had to pause and say, "Why a
conventional?" And they said, "Well, I'm
reading to use my VA home loan." [music]
So, yeah.
>> Yeah. You don't need to wait to use your
VA loan. You if if you've bought and
sold before, you still can use your VA
loan so long your entitlement allows.
Even if you have your
>> [music]
>> uh previous home at your previous uh
duty station, you can still have or
purchase another home here at Fort Hood
using your VA benefits once again. So,
you can have both of those loans open at
the same time [music]
so long you can qualify and so long you
have enough remaining entitlement uh to
make that purchase.
>> Awesome. So, Jacob, what do you think
makes the VA home loan so [music]
powerful?
>> Yeah, so number one is the 0% down
payment option. So for [music] most
people that opens a lot of opportunities
to be able to afford the home. Secondly,
there is no mortgage insurance on the VA
loan. So that extends your uh [music]
buying power being that you're not going
to have to pay that money as a part of
your mortgage payment. Um competitive
interest rates is another big advantage
of VA loans. Also, seller credits. You
can have seller credits cover your
closing costs. You can have seller
credits pay down some of your debt
items. And you can have seller credits
even buy down your rate permanently
which is very powerful as well. Um and
then the last one there's multiple more
uh but another benefit is [music] on the
refinance side then you can roll in it
is an option you can roll in all of your
closing cost into the loan.
>> Cool. Jacob and I recently had a deal
together. We had an active [music] duty
service member and they were pretty
tight on money and we were able because
the market is what it is. We're in such
a buyer market, we were able to ask for
max allowable concessions. Um, the
seller was really ready to offload their
home. We got a great deal on the home.
They were able to get all their closing
costs covered, no down payment, buy down
their rate, and they even had extra
money that they could use, and [music] I
think he paid a few thousand off without
Home Depot credit card.
>> Exactly. Right. So, that was
>> pretty powerful. You can't do that with
any other loan types. U So, as far as we
can stretch to seller concessions at
your benefit, we're going to do it.
>> Yeah. More buying power for [music] you.
That's right.
>> Yeah. How the process actually works
getting started.
>> Yeah. So, step one is to get
preapproved. So, work on getting your
pre-approval. During that time, we can
also simultaneously work on your getting
your certificate of eligibility through
the VA. I can help on that request.
Also, it is highly advised that you
partner with a very VA friendly and
experienced agent like Andrea here. Um,
that's going to be [music] very
important um throughout your process.
Um, once you get those parts in place
and once you're pre-approved, then you
can start making offers [music] and
going through the home buying process.
>> Yes. And of course, you know, I do get
calls a lot of times before someone's
connected with a lender. And that's
okay, too. We can discuss what your ones
are and what your [music] musthaves and
your situation is, and I can connect you
with local reputable lenders. Then, at
that point, Jacob will have you fill out
an application and go through that
process. And then really once [music]
you are preapproved, that's really going
to tell us what your buying power looks
like. You know, you don't want to go
looking at a $300,000 home and then find
out that you only qualify for a $220,000
home. Or alternatively, think that you
only qualify for a $220,000 home, but
you can afford a $300,000 home. So once
we know that, we can [music] get you
started on looking at home, get you
under contract, and then really go
through the entirety of the process in
terms of um [music] getting you clear to
close on your financing, um appraisals,
home warranties, and and that entire
process. [music] And actually, while
we're talking about appraisals, um I
think just touching back on the
misconceptions briefly, I've had people
ask, even though I have my VA home loan
benefits, [music] should I do a
conventional loan because I have more
money to put down? Is there a certain
circumstance [music] where using a
conventional loan or another loan type
is better than using a VA [music] home
loan?
>> Yeah. So, I'll touch on appraisals
first. They're hardly different than any
other loan type appraisal. The [music]
main difference on the VA appraisal
requirements is that the home is safe,
sanitary, and habitable. Those are the
main uh things that appraisers will go
to look at in in addition to the
appraised value, of course, but the the
main difference that they're going to
look at when appraising [music] or and
uh evaluating the house. Now to when it
makes more sense to use a conventional
loan over the VA loan, there are certain
circumstances if the numbers work, but
in most cases it [music] doesn't make
sense unless the property itself won't
qualify for the VA [music] loan.
>> There are a lot of agents or sellers
that will say, "Sure, I'll be willing to
take a VA home loan." Well, as an
experienced [music] agent, if I know
that you're using your VA home loan
benefits and you say, "Andre, I really
like this house." And I mean a lot of
times I can just look at the pictures or
u information on the home and [music]
see that it is not going going to be in
a condition that will pass a VA home
inspection, VA appraisal, that's going
to save us a lot of leg work on the
front end. And in that circumstance, if
you have the money and you say, "Hey,
you know what? I know it may cost me a
little bit more. I may have to put more
money down. That payment might look a
little bit different, but I really want
that home." Maybe in that circumstance,
using a conventional loan might be
better for you.
>> Absolutely. We'll leave you with just a
few tips in the central Texas market. We
are in an incredibly competitive market
as of today. Of course, things [music]
are always changing, but they've been
pretty competitive for a while now. And
we're in a buyer market. There's
probably a lot of people are scared with
interest rates, but there are so many
ways to get lowered interest rates.
[music]
Um whether that's buying them down,
having the seller cover some of those,
builders [music] are paying a ton to buy
down rates. But this is really a buyer
market. So the tip for me is if you can
buy a home right now, do it because
there's a lot of buying power [music]
for
>> and there's a lot of opportunities for
buyers to get those seller concessions.
In other markets, you don't get that
opportunity. So [music] in this market,
you can have the opportunity to get your
closing costs covered and also use a
portion of those seller credits to buy
your rate down to alleviate some [music]
of the rate um concerns that are out
there. Mhm. So those seller concessions
and then builders are very VA friendly.
They [music] often offer a lot of
incentives specifically to VA buyers.
Whether that certain packages we can get
for you. Maybe they're offering
appliance packages or a [music] lot of
times they'll do lesser money for
earnest money or security deposit up
front. A lot of times they might do a
[music] certain amount for nonVA buyers,
but when they hear that you're um using
your VA benefits, [music] they extend
that and give you a very low one. And so
because um Texas is so [music] VA
friendly, a lot of benefits there with
>> Absolutely. And especially here in
central Texas being Fort Hood is such a
large installation, [music] the the area
is so used to and is and is wellversed
in um and accepting of VA loans. [music]
So, all of our BA buyers out there, they
they're not any less competitive than
any other loan types, especially here,
which is fantastic. [music]
>> Yeah. And then the the final tip is
probably going to be timing is
everything. So, when you [music] get
those PCS orders, contact us immediately
so that we can help time [music]
your orders with your closing.
>> That's right. Yeah. Everything is about
timing. So long as we get everything in
order, we'll be able to backwards plan
of when you arrive from your PCS, when
you can close, all those things we'll be
able to to iron out.
>> Okay. And then just to finalize [music]
that, can someone purchase before they
are stationed?
>> Yes, absolutely. So you don't have to
[music] currently be at that duty
station in person to be able to
purchase. So you can purchase in advance
in preparation for your arrival.
Absolutely.
>> VA home loans are an incredible benefit.
Using them strategically can really help
you [music] build long-term wealth and
not just buy a home. So whether you're
PCSing to the area or settling [music]
down post service, we'd love to help you
make the most of your VA benefits.
>> Absolutely. [music]
Reach out anytime with your VA loan
questions. We'll be here to help you
work towards your pre-approval and we'll
walk you through the entire process.
>> I'll leave Jacob's information in the
comments below along with my free
relocation guide. And if you're new to
the channel, don't forget to like,
subscribe, [music] and click the bell
notification so that you can stay
uptodate on all local insights and real
estate things happening here in Central
Texas. You can also leave your VA
questions below in the comments so we
know what to answer next. Till next
time.
>> [music]